Nicholas Hoyt

UX/Interaction Designer

Phone:	Address:	
Email:	LinkedIn:	https://www.linkedin.com/in/nhoy

Interaction/UX design professional with over 25 years of experience specializing in user interface design for web applications and browser extensions. Experience with user research and contextual inquiry, creating paper and wireframe prototypes, design specifications and conceptual models, and conducting usability testing that includes web accessibility evaluation.

Experience

2005-09 - present

Interaction Designer, Front-End Developer

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Designed and developed the SkipTo Landmarks & Headings browser extension for Chrome and Firefox, released in June 2021. The extension enables keyboard-only users to efficiently navigate the important headings and landmarks on a web page. A complete description of the SkipTo extension with installation links is available at https://skipto.github.io.

Served as lead designer and developer for the A11yFirst Project in the creation of five accessibility-focused plugins for CKEditor. Released in 2019, the plugins proactively guide content authors as they edit, enabling them to create documents that meet WCAG accessibility requirements. More details are available on the CKEditor Addons website.

Designed and collaboratively developed the Alnspector browser extension for Firefox, which performs detailed evaluations of web pages across twelve categories of WCAG and ARIA accessibility requirements. Alnspector is being updated to version 2.0 with significant enhancements for release in 2022. Available for installation at the Firefox Addons website.

Served as lead designer and developer of the Accessibility Bookmarklets, web accessibility visualization tools compatible with all major browsers. Full documentation and installation instructions are available at https://accessibility-bookmarklets.org/.

1999-08 - 2005-09

Interaction Designer, Front-End Developer

Web UI, Wheaton, IL

As an independent contractor, provided software design and development services with an emphasis on interaction design and front-end development for various corporate clients, including ABN AMRO, Accenture, Allstate Insurance, DeVry University, Fidelity Investments, HOLT Value Associates and the Illinois Institute of Technology.

1997-08 - 1999-08

Interaction Designer, Front-End Developer

Fidelity Investments, Marlborough, MA

Served as lead interaction designer in the redesign of NetBenefits, a web application providing retirement savings account access to over one million customers. Improved the user experience through contextual inquiry, task flow analysis and usability testing.

Designed and developed retirement investing tools for 401k.com, Fidelity's website for institutional investors. Tools included the Contribution Calculator, Withdrawal Calculator and Take Home Pay Calculator.

Nicholas Hoyt

Education

B.A. in Computer Science, University of Massachusetts Boston, 1991 Graduated summa cum laude

Introduction to Programming in Pascal, Harvard Extension School, 1988 Grade: A; Undergraduate credits: 4

Jazz Composition & Arranging major, Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA Seven full-time semesters, 1981–1984, GPA of 3.85/4.0

Skills

Interaction Design

- · Requirements gathering and analysis
- · Development of conceptual models, personas, scenarios
- Essential use cases, user role- and task-models
- · Creation of wireframes using Sketch, OmniGraffle and Figma

User Research & Information Architecture

- · Field observations, contextual interviews
- · Task-modeling workshops, wants and needs analysis
- · Card sorting exercises, focus groups
- · Paper prototyping, low-fidelity prototypes

Usability Analysis & Testing

- · Creation of interactive HTML/JavaScript prototypes
- · Facilitation of remote and lab-based usability testing
- · Quantitative and qualitative analysis of test results

Front-End Development

- · JavaScript, HTML, CSS, DOM scripting and event handling
- · WCAG 2.0 accessibility requirements
- · Responsive design
- · Web components, WebExtensions API

Resources

Portfolio

- Design Portfolio
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings for Chrome
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings for Firefox
- · A11yFirst plugins for CKEditor
- · Accessibility Bookmarklets